A Guide to the Papers of the Trist, Burke, and Randolph Families, 1832-1886, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Trist, Burke, and Randolph Families 1832-1886, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5096-a
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the Library by the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1955 June 27.
Biographical/Historical Information
Nicholas P. Trist: American diplomat, b. Charlottesville, Va. Trist attended West Point, studied law under Thomas Jefferson, whose granddaughter he married, and was private secretary to Andrew Jackson. He served as U.S. consul (1833-1841) in Havana, Cuba, and was chief clerk of the Dept. of State when he was sent (1847) to Mexico as a special agent to conduct negotiations to end the Mexican War. A short armistice was reached after the battles of Contreras and Churubusco (August, 1847), but negotiations were unsuccessful and war was resumed. President Polk had Trist recalled. Trist had reopened negotiations before his recall arrived and decided to ignore the order. He succeeded in negotiating the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. Polk supported the treaty but declared Trist in disgrace. Trist did not recover his unpaid salary and expenses until 1871.
Scope and Content
Chiefly the correspondence (drafts) and notes of Nicholas P. Trist relating to his activities in the peace negotiations with Mexico, 1847-1848, and to his controversy with Generals Scott and Pillow. Persons mentioned and correspondents include James Buchanan, Caleb Cushing, James L. Freaner, Henry W. Hilliard, Commodore M.C. Perry, Major General Gideon Johnson Pillow, Major General Winfield Scott, and R.C. Winthrop. Map of northern Mexico with annotations and signed by R.E. Lee.
The remaining portion of the collection pertains to the Trist and related families and includes the correspondence of Martha Jefferson Trist Burke, J.W. Burke, Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge, Sydney Coolidge, E. H. Janne, Lewis Carter Randolph, Mary Jefferson Randolph, Mary Page Randolph, and Virginia Jefferson Trist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series. Series I: Correspondence of Nicholas P. Trist; Series II: Documents of Nicholas P. Trist Relating to the Mexican War; Series III: Correspondence of the Trist, Burke and Randolph Families; and, Series IV: Miscellaneous Documents. The series are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence of Nicholas P. Trist
  - [Nicholas P. Trist], [Mexico], to James Buchanan, Secretary of State, [Washington D.C.], 1847 July 21 to August 13, AL, 33 pp. on 11 l.; copies; partly written in cipher code. (Box-folder 1:1)
    #5096-a.
  - Key for cipher code used in Nicholas P. Trist's Letter to James Buchanan, 1847 July 21 to August 13, n.d., AD, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - [Nichols Trist], Puebla and Ayobla, Mexico, to James Buchanan, Washington D.C., 1847 July 21 to August 13, AL, 14 pp. on 4 l.; draft. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Draft of Trist's letter to James Buchanan; not written in cipher. #5096-a.
  - Extract from the note of the Mexican Commissioners, 1847 September 6, AD, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Nicholas P. Trist's Annotated copy of the "Leonidas letter," [1847 October 23], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:5)
    A copy of the Leonidas letter to the editors of the New Orleans Delta (printed September 10, 1847) which praised the performance of General Gideon Pillow as the victor of the battles of Contreras and Churubusco and denigrated the performance of General Winfield Scott. The letter was allegedly carried from Mexico by James L. Freaner, a reporter. The false attribution of victory to Pillow led to his "technical arrest" and court martial.
    Trist's copy ("made for me by Lt. Hamilton") includes his notes concerning the receipt of the original. Trist states that this "is an exact copy (interlineations, cancellings + all) of the paper placed in my hands on the 23rd day of October 1847, by James L. Freaner, who stated that it had been placed in his hands by Genl. Pillow, at Miscoae, with the request to transmit it to the Delta or to embody it in the account of the battle which he (Freaner) should send."
  - James L. Freaner to Major General Gideon T. Pillow, 1847 November 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; copy. (Box-folder 1:6)
    The verso contains notes by Nicholas P. Trist about his encounter with James L. Freaner. #5096-a.
  - Nicholas P. Trist, [Mexico], to [James Buchanan] Secretary of State, [Washington D.C.], 1847 December 4, ALS copy, 6 pp. on 6 l. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Nicholas P. Trist, [Mexico], to James Buchanan, [Washington D.C.], 1847 December 6, ALS, 81 pp. on 81 l. (Box-folder 1:8)
    "Smooth draft." #5096-a.
  - Nicholas P. Trist, [Mexico], to James Buchanan, [Washington D.C.], 1847 December 6, AL, 3 pp on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:9)
    "Preface to the letter of December 4th, 1847." #5096-a.
  - James Buchanan, Washington D.C., to Nicholas P. Trist, 1847 December 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - N[icholas] T[rist], Headquarters, U.S. Army, Mexico, to Commodore M. C. Perry, Vera Cruz, Mexico, 1848 January 18, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Ja[me]s L. Freaner, Charleston, S.C., to James Buchanan, Washington D.C., 1848 February, ANS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:12)
    "Copy of note given to Freaner in cypher, for him to send in that form by Telegraph from Charleston." #5096-a.
  - N[icholas P.] Trist, Mexico City, Mexico, to Major General Winfield Scott, [Mexico City, Mexico], 1848 March 20, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - N[icholas P.] Trist, Washington D.C., to [S.C. Ridgely], 1848 June 21, ALS, 16 pp. on 4 l.; four copies. (Box-folder 1:14)
    "Extracts from a letter addressed by me to the Judge Advocate of the Pillow Court of Inquiry, dated Washington, June 21, 1848." #5096-a.
  - [Nicholas P. Trist], West Chester, PA, to [Henry W. Hilliard], [Washington D.C.], 1848 July 28, ALS, 5 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - N[icholas] T[rist], West Chester, PA, to R[obert] C[harles] Winthrop, Washington D.C., 1848 August 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; rough draft and fair copy. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Th[omas] J[efferson] T[rist] to Nicholas Trist, [1851], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Series II: Documents of Nicholas P. Trist Relating to the Mexican War
  - Nicholas P. Trist's notebook written at Donaldsville, Louisiana, 1822-1823, AMss, 44 pp. on 11 l. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Rough drafts of letter and papers transmitted to the House of Representatives by Nicholas P. Trist, 1848, Amss, ca.144 pp. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Rough draft of latter and papers transmitted to the House of Representatives by Nicholas P. Trist, 1848, Amss, ca.193 pp. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Gideon J. Pillow's Statement on the Trist-Pillow Controversy, 1848 March 21, ADs, 1 p.; two copies. (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Rough Draft of Nicholas P. Trist's Statement Concerning Caleb Cushing's Appointment as a Brigadier General in the U.S. Army, 1848 May, AMs, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Draft of Nicholas P. Trist's Statement Concerning Caleb Cushing's Actions as a Brigadier General in the U.S. Army, [1848 May], AMs, 11 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Rough draft of a statement made by Nichols P. Trist concerning his actions in Mexico, [1851?], AMs. (Box-folder 1:24)
    5096-a.
  - Rough Draft of a statement made by Nicholas P. Trist concerning his actions in Mexico: Appendix notes, [1851?], AMs. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - The War with Mexico, Propositions, 1856 February, AMs, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Drafts of Official Dispatches from Nicholas P. Trist to the Department of State, n.d., AMs, 12 pp. on 10 l. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Drafts of document about the Mexican War, n.d., AMs, 8 pp. on 7 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings on the Mexican War Peace Settlement and the Trist-Pillow Controversy, 1847-1857, 16 items. (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper clippings on the Mexican War Peace Settlement and the Trist-Pillow controversy, 1847-1857, Photocopies of documents in folder above. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts, [ca. 1848], AD, 2 pp on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Blank Official Stationary, n.d., 13 l. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Memoranda, n.d., AD, 1 p. #5096-a. (Box-folder 1:33)
    "Respecting papers, copies of which are wanting for my acct. of Mexican affairs."
  - List of dispatches, n.d., AD, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:34)
    A list of dispatches, numbered 15-24 and dated 1847 Sep.4-Dec.26. #5096-a.
- Series III: Correspondence of the Trist, Burke and Randolph Families
  - E. H. Randolph, Elk Hill, to Lewis Randolph, Washington D.C., 1832 November 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - J. G. Wright, Guyandotte, VA, to Lewis Randolph, Washington D.C., 1835 January 26, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. Brittle along old folds. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Letter and Papers Relating to the case of Ezra Thurber, 1836 January 6, AL and ANs copies, 13 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Concerning claims upon a foreign government by a U.S. citizen. #5096-a.
  - [Jane Hollins Randolph], Edge-hill, to Lewis Randolph, Washington D.C., 1836 March 3, AL, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. Broken at old folds. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Sidney Coolidge, Cambridge to Mr. Burke, 1860 January 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - [Unidentified Correspondent] to "Dearest Aunt," 1865 April 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:6)
    Mentions the assassination of Abraham Lincoln. #5096-a.
  - V[irginia] J[efferson] Trist, Alexandria, to Mary [P. Randolph], 1871 January 8, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Discusses the health of Nicholas Trist and the birth of Edmund Jefferson Burke, son of Martha Jefferson Trist Burke. #5096-a.
  - [Martha Jefferson Trist Burke] to "Dearest Ellen," 1871 February 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:8)
    Discusses the health of family members, chiefly Cornelia Jefferson Randolph. #5096-a.
  - V.[irginia] J.[efferson] Trist, Alexandria, to Mary [Page Randolph], 1872 January 7, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:9)
    Health, family news; encloses family photographs [not present]. #5096-a.
  - V.[irginia] J.[efferson] Trist, Alexandria to Mary [Page Randolph], 1873 January 6-9, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l.; with AN, N.[ichoals] P. [Trist] to "Dear Mary" above salutation. (Box-folder 2:10)
    Fmaily news; death of Mary Wythe. #5096-a.
  - E.[li] H. Janney, Alexandria, VA, to Nicholas P. Trist, 1873 May 20, ALS, 1 p.; ANS, Nicholas P. Trist, below body of letter. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Concerning patents in Austria, Belgium, Italy and Prussia. #5096-a..
  - Dyer, Beadle and Company to H.[ore] B.[rowse] Trist, [1873] May 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 2:12)
    Concerning patents for a "car coupling" in Austria, Hungary and Belgium. #5096-a.
  - Eli H. Janney to H. B. T[rist], 1873 June 6, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Written on the inside of an envelope addressed to Nicholas P. Trist, and containing Trist's notes on Janney's business proposal. #5096-a.
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist and N[icholas] P. Trist, Alexandria, VA, to Mary Jefferson Randolph, Rockville, MD, 1873 October 29, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Alexandria, VA, to Mary [P. Randolph], 1874, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Martha Jefferson Trist Burke to Mary [P. Randolph], 1876 January 21, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Ellen Wayles Coolidge, Boston, MA, to Mrs. John W. Burke, Alexandria, VA, 1876 April 8, ALS, 5 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope; postmarked but unreadable. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Alexandria, VA, to Mary [P. Randolph], 1877 September 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Alexandria, VA, to Unidentified, 1880 May 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:19)
  - [Virginia Jefferson Trist], Alexandria, VA, to Mrs. J. W. Burke, Taylorsville, VA, 1881 March 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; Postmarked Alexandria, VA, March 3. (Box-folder 2:20)
    Envelope contains a note by Trist stating, that this was "the last letter received from my most precious mother, and the last she ever wrote." #5096-a.
  - Martha Jefferson Trist Burke, Alexandria, VA, to Unidentified, 1881 August 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:21)
  - [Virginia Jefferson Trist], Georgetown, to Mrs. John Burke, Alexandria, VA, 1881 October 12, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope; docketed; Postmarked Georgetown, 1881 October 13. (Box-folder 2:22)
  - H. C. Stearns, Exeter, NH, to Mrs. M[artha] J[efferson] Burke, Alexandria, VA, [1883] May 26, ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope; Postmarked Alexandria, VA, May 27. (Box-folder 2:23)
    With a note on envelope stating "about my mother from Miss H. L. Stearns." #5096-a.
  - M[ary] P[age] Randolph to "Pattie" [Virginia Jefferson Trist Burke], 1884 January 1, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:24)
    With enclosed greenery. #5096-a.
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Alexandria, VA, to [Mrs. Burke], Washington DC, [1884] March 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; Postmarked Alexandria, VA, March 31. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Envelope addressed to Mrs. L. R. Mukleham with a note on the lower left hand side "for Mrs. Burke." #5096-a.
  - [?] Randolph, Berryville, to Lewis Randolph, Washington D.C., n.y. February 13, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 2:26)
    With partial wax seal; brittle along old folds. #5096-a.
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Alexandria, VA, to Mrs. Burke, Washington DC, n.y. April 1, APCS, 1 p.; Postmarked Alexandria, VA, April 1. (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Virginia Jefferson Trist, Washington DC, to Mrs. J. W. Burke, Alexandria, VA, n.y. July 30, APCS, 1 p.; Postmarked Washington DC, July 30. #5096-a. (Box-folder 2:28)
  - M[ary] P[age] R[andolph] to "Pattie", n.y. November 13, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:29)
    Letter written on the verson of an envelope addressed to Mary Page Randolph and postmarked Alexandria, VA May 21. #5096-a.
  - Ellen R.D. to "Pattie" Trist, n.d. Thursday, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Envelope addressed to Mrs. John Burke from Unidentified, 1886 November 1[4], Envelope only; Postmarked Jacksonville, November 1[4]. (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Partial envelope received Saturday, January 5, n.y. (Box-folder 2:32)
    Postmarked Alexandria, VA, January 4. #5096-a.
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Documents
  - Three Pamphlets on Cooking and a Blotter, ca. 1873, #5096-a. (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Recipes by Unidentified, n.d., 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Two Household Account and Recipe Books, n.d. (Box-folder 2:35)
  - Homemade Booklet Written in Spanish, n.d., AMs, 30 pp. on 8 l. Bound together with string. (Box-folder 2:36)
  - Miscellaneous Letter Covers and wrappers, n.d., Eight items. (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, n.d. (Box-folder 2:38)
    1. Notes on authors 2. Fragment mentioning Carlos Lauda's Letter 3. Various notes 4. Notes on the length of a pendulum 5. Notes on the "Historia de Nueva Espana" 6. List of Classical authors 7. Excerpt from a letter or article on the start of the war with Mexico 8. Brief excerpt from a text by Francis Quarles 9. One leaf of printed matter from an unidentified source
  - Sketch of United States Troop Movements in the Battle of Mexico, [1847], 1 p. on 1 l. On tracing paper. (Oversize V-13)
    OS Box V-13.
  - Cover of Viage pintoresco y arqueologico de Mexico, con 50 estampas litografiadas, gue representen sus ciudades principales, los monumentos de antiguedad mas notables y los trages nacionales, by Vicente Garcia Torres, 1840, OS Box V-13. (Oversize V-13)